So um in previous talks
we've brushed on the topic but never
really gone into it in depth.
So
how how would how could we define what a
method is in the sense that we talk about it?
is in the sense that we talk about it?
Um and why is it a problem? Because I
mean so there's do talk about like the
noble method and uh you know the
sometimes the noble path is described as
like the the proper method proper
practice but how we define
but how we define
method in the wrong
sense that shouldn't be
Yeah. Are you asking what is ordinarily
seen or conceived as a method and how is
that different from the noble method
which is the noble path or the penation
as it's described in the sutras.
So like what's the difference between
just having
um you're not improvising of course. So
we're not saying like don't do a method
means like you kind of decide on the
spot and you don't have a plan. You just
kind of go with the flow or something. M
but it also doesn't mean that you do
that type of method. So what is where is
it that you know having like a an idea
about what you should do and uh and a
kind of
broad guideline where is it that that
becomes a method or a technique the
other word that we could use.
One one things would be
to know you just go somewhere ask a
question and then someone give you
something to do and then you just say
okay right I just do that but then that
doesn't imply any type of understanding
you just kind of repeat mechanically the
same things whatever it is over and over
and over again hoping for a different
result while you actually do the same
all the time. Mhm. But so what why is so
why is it that a problem? Like you know
because it could lead to results that
people think are useful like it could
lead to states of calm
to maybe novel perceptions or
experiences and being able to deal with life better
and being able to deal with life better
or whatever whatever people are looking
for. So why is it that that doesn't
apply to the practice? Like why is it
to the practice? Like why is it
wrong even if it's the best gives you
the best uh benefits and and the best uh
kind of quote unquote spiritual
development? Why is it not the same as the spiritual
Why is it not the same as the spiritual
development that the Buddha was
teaching? Yes, that's the question.
Yeah. [Music]
[Music]
Well, well, one one thing that I see is
that it's just like, okay, I go
somewhere, I learned this technique and
then I keep repeating that. But the fact
is that I never kind of question myself
whether if
I kind
of no it's not quite quite what I want
to say. It's more like um so if my
experience is kind of affected by kind
of ignorance whatever I learn come
through this lens in my experience. So
if someone teach me something and I
think I understand what he's talking
about this understanding is coming through
this understanding is coming through
kind of ignorance and my kind of
experience of that. So if like the kind
of teaching that is given to me doesn't
try to highlight the fact that right now
you might do this you might do that but
you have to kind of improve your
understanding well then there is no hope
for me to understand anything because I
kind of assume that already know but
this knowledge is confined within the
fact that I'm ignorant in the first
place but so okay but how would you
remedy that situation because from that
point of view everything you hear is
going to share that characteristic Like
some instructions might be kind of
more superficial, others might be less
so, but fundamentally you still all of
it is happening within ignorance as you
said or or is being received by the
ignorance ignorant framework. So how
would you what's the missing element there
you what's the missing element there
that wouldn't allow you to develop
knowledge even if you do the right
technique that the Buddha himself gave
you you do it for 100
years. Well, you see, it seems to me
that the problem with these methods and
techniques is that once you accept them,
the method or the technique comes first
and your let's say subjective state of
mind or intentions come second. That is
why the technique remains static.
Um, and the assumption is that the
technique doesn't change. you you just
keep applying it and gradually through
time things will begin to unfold
which ties into the ignorance that you
were talking about. If being affected by
ignorance you accept a technique as
right then that acceptance and the
criteria are part of that ignorance.
So, so you can keep following that but
it will not lead you out of
ignorance except if that technique has
as its main characteristic that it shows
your subjective state of mind and
intentions and tells you to put that
first. But when that is the instruction
that technique can on no accounts ever
become really a technique the way we are
now discussing it because those mind
states and and intentions are
impermanent. They change. So you have to
put that first and move with that which
is the reversal of how technique is
usually applied. That's why I don't see
how ordinarily methods and techniques
lead inwards or let's say out of
ignorance. Yeah.
So so that's the thing. So it's not it's
not even the that the content of a
technique is bad. It's not like, oh, you
you did technique number one, you should
have done technique number two instead.
Well, that actually also happens like
it's not uncommon in certain traditions
to to have a sense of false progress.
Like you do level one and then you
fiddle around with that for a few months
and then you can now apply for
meditation method technique number two
and then people can go through that and
then weekend here, initiation there,
special transmission here, right? and so
on. Um and then you just keep
accumulating slightly different methods
and techniques and and you think that
that is progress whereas actually uh it
it doesn't reveal anything about what is
now subjectively for you going on.
Exactly. So, so but what is
that why is it important to to have uh
that subjective dimension and and what
is it more specifically because you know
you could
also I mean from that point of view
people would also argue that no no this
is like getting me to understand my own
mind how can you say that it's not
teaching me about subjective well
elements because that state of mind is
already there and so you deciding right
now should I practice meditation method
technique number 1 2 3 4 5 or whatever
you have accumulated in the course of
your life that choice is already coming
out of certain intentions and is already
affected by certain mind states but the
difficulty is that that's precisely not
seen if there is this kind of obsession
or almost fetishism with accumulating
different methods and techniques you you
think or even the same one just even if
you don't. Well, so we so so even if
it's one, but that's actually already
quite uncommon to find somebody who
sticks to one method and technique, even
if it's still the wrong understanding of
of method and technique. In a sense, it
would be better. I would almost argue,
but still it it's it it could still go
wrong basically. Yeah. Well, yeah. If
you stick to one at least you kind of
assume you're not like
um it's not such a
coarse dependence and assumption of your
own uh qualification to decide what is
useful and what is not useful. At least
you're kind of recognizing like okay I
if I'm ignorant how am I supposed to be
able to decide when to do this one and
when to do the other one. So at the very
least you would um stick to one like as
a Buddha did you stick to one and then
you master it and then you realize it
doesn't meet to the goal so then you
move on but even then of course that's
not the right attitude but the the kind
of um mixing and matching and like
cherrypicking a little bit of this and a
little bit of that that's even more
inauthentic than just just doing one one
single technique. But so the the thing
is like so what is that um
um
like what is that kind of
a subjective element that you that you
mentioned like more more specifically so
you mentioned the intention.
So why is
that or let's say how is that properly
recognized if not through a technique?
You mean whether intention is wholesome
or unwome? Yeah. Or whatever the
intention is. Yeah.
Well, that's precisely the whole point.
Like so so let's say let's say going
back to what I said before, you scrap
the techniques you were doing. Yeah. And
then your technique becomes watching
your intentions. Mhm.
So would that
be the right
practice? Well, certainly closer, but
that's not your question now. Mhm. Um
well, it would involve more than just
let's say in an impersonal
way observing your
intentions because and awesome
intentions then you shouldn't act out of
to begin with. Um so that is um closer
and but but you see now we get into the
domain of like precepts and sensory
strength because th those precepts they
are in a sense fixed although one's
understanding of them can can be refined
but certain things you should you just
shouldn't do regardless of the situation
that you find yourself in. So that is
actually so if people have
difficulty totally giving up this idea
of methods or techniques then to stick
to observing your precepts would be in
my opinion closer to a method or
technique than what is normally
presented as meditation methods and
techniques. That's not one thing. But
your your question then still like is it
just a matter of observing whether
intentions are wholesome or unh
wholesome? Well, um that in and of
itself is also already an attitude that
you bring. Like now I'm going to look at
my intentions. Like you could become
very suspicious about yourself or you
might have a sort of a background
attitude like I should be on the lookout
for something that is unh wholesome or
that's not supposed to happen and so on.
And that whole attitude can also already
be tainted by what's unh wholesome. So
you can't also now make a formula and
say just observe your intentions and
then assume that that's always right
because to observe intentions is from
your subjective point of view that
attention is also not always the same.
Yeah. Yeah. So, so
basically if
you if you turn even the right I mean of
course even all these methods that exist
today they originated in some or were
influenced in some way or another by
things that are found in the sutas. But
the problem is if you take anything and
you make it static like you said in that
way then um it's just a matter of time
until it devolves into something
completely different. You might be doing
it rightly in the beginning like asking
yourself if you if you never question
yourself about your intentions and then
you suddenly begin doing that then of
course it's going to it's going to kind
of point you to that direction let's say
of where your intentions are. which is
not wrong. Exactly. But the problem is
that that very impulse to make it into
like a fixed thing that I can just
repeat. That in itself will make it not
be right anymore. So, so the point
being, as I said before, it's not even
that it's one technique that's wrong and
then the other ones are fine. Like, oh,
give up body scanning and then watch
your intentions instead.
The entire attitude. Yeah. of wanting to
get a formula for it, wanting to get a
recipe for it that needs to be given up.
Yeah. Because you are essentially
looking for something which is
permanent by holding on to that attitude
of wanting a method or a technique. How
is that now going to reveal the
impermanency of phenomena that the
Buddha is talking about? No. Well, you
you are looking you might be looking for
impermanence but the thing
is that entire dimension of your
experience that actually matters which
is like you said the subjective part
um which I mean it it's it it goes hand
in hand because you know that usually
the view is like oh you you need to be
perfectly objective you need to destroy
your subjectivity that's how you get rid
of the self that's now another problem
exactly so so then By getting into this
attitude of okay, just the object, just
the object, just the object and
completely disregarding even more the
whole like shadow
of why are you doing this in the first
place? Uh-huh. There are like as the
Buddha said actually there's there's one
whole suta
where this Brahman
um came to ask not the Buddha um ananda
like uh oh the blessed one he was a
meditator and he he praised all kinds of
meditation. That's right. Yeah. And then
uh and says no he he wasn't he didn't
praise all kind of meditation and he
said what's the kind of meditation that
he didn't praise he said it's when
someone harboring sensual desire
internally meditates overmeditates undermeditates
meditates overmeditates undermeditates
mismeditates
mismeditates uh harboring ill will
internally harboring um laziness
internally so all the five hindrances
um And see that that description there
like premeditates, overmeditates,
undermeditates, mismeditates. The whole point there it's
mismeditates. The whole point there it's
like any direction that he goes. It
doesn't matter where where it is. It
doesn't matter whether
it's watching your breath or
um doing body scanning or doing noting
or doing mantras or doing meta or doing
anything under the sun.
the the problem there is not that. The
problem is that he's harboring these
things internally.
So because he he's kind of overlooking
that entire dimension and then focusing
on what's in front of it. Kind of like
there's actually the same description
happens in that suta with with the
thoroughb bread like the the two horses
and it says like the first one just
looks at the
hay and uh yeah it just thinks hey like
like just completely um absorbed
actually literally like absorption. And
then the other one he actually wait no
what does
the horse trainer want me to do today?
Yeah we did all talk on that. Yeah
exactly. So that's that direction where
that's that direction that cannot be
um made static that dimension of that
horse asking himself what does the
trainer want me to do today? Obviously
in that example, yeah, you could just
ask yourself that question every time
and you'll be fine. But in this case,
the principle of essentially the
principle of
unisara is is something that
um will tend to kind of to put it
certain way like it's going to be like a
slippery fish most especially if you
haven't been um sufficiently restrained
and and keeping the precepts and stuff.
So you will get like a like a sense of
it like okay right now I am aware of my
intention properly but the next time you have the
properly but the next time you have the
same information the same teaching the
same explanation and you try to do it
again but now clearly it's not working
and so you start to see then that
actually even that
description that you
get I mean that's part of the problem
with the method like you think that the
practice is in that description like you
said before you just every time you
apply it as long as it's faithful to the
description it's correct but if you go
this route you will start to realize
actually there's there isn't even uh a
guarantee that because I remember
exactly what the instruction was that I
will do it properly next time
because like I said it just slips away
from you like the the intention just uh
even though it's there because you're
not developed
sufficiently in authenticity in sense
restraint and you're used to acting out
of pressure
um as a as your default
then everything you do is kind of like
to continue with that momentum. Yeah. So
then as a result the possibility of
stopping the momentum of acting out
becomes more and more unpleasant. So in
other words, you could actually
recognize what your intention is at any
given time and give it up. But the fact
that you carry this momentum with your
ignorance and with your unrestrained
actions on top of it means that makes it
even harder harder pretty much to look
at that direction where the intention is
because it's going to be unpleasant. It
means like, "Oh, wait. I've been acting
out of of greed, aversion, delusion this
whole time." And uh this mind is it's
like like the dog, you've been letting
it go there in the same direction for a
very good amount of time and then now it
doesn't want to stop because it already
caught something. It can smell it from
who knows how many kilometers away and
now it's just running towards it. And uh
that's that's basically the
the that's what makes it even harder to
attend in that direction of of
um the opposite let's say of the the
counterpart or where your attention is
which is
you could in the most um acute sense
describe it as as the intention. It's
the sign of the mind that we discussed
before. Yes.
Um so so it's like it's like
the it's almost like the first
point from which you start like let's
say you you kept the precepts you you
took them on you have been restrained on
that external
level and then after that what do you do
from that first point what do you do
and the problem is like with with these
techniques and
methods you would assume like no no even
I mean you the person wouldn't be aware
of course
but that first point would be tainted
like you said with um various
defilements that they're not aware of
but then because this because the stuff
that comes afterwards like the
perceptions the insights the experiences
whatever it might
be seems to be right or whatever because
you think it's a result of your method.
So you automatically assume that it's
progress. Yeah. But the whole point is
like it doesn't matter how right that
that stuff
is the first point from which it comes
or you could say the foundation from
which it comes is that first intention
of whatever defilement you were acting
out of in the beginning. So it could
have been anticipation, craving,
um, whatever, aversion, curiosity even
like some people just genuinely just uh
just for a little while, see what
happens in the night or or Yeah.
curiosity because you want to have these
special experiences and and then um
nothing to do with like sense of urgency
and freedom from suffering and uh and
those intentions are behind the that
that whole thing that you're doing like
imagine you kind of um I don't know you
you decided to go somewhere and in that
period of time you're going to have to
pass through uh such and such a place.
Well, it's not that the intention to go
to that place was there only at that
first second when you decided, okay, let
me go there. No, that that entire
journey doesn't matter how many
kilometers you've walked, that
intention of you going to such and such
a place is with you there. So that
entire time if the intention wasn't
wholesome that entire time everything
you're doing is polluted by that
intention. Mhm. So that's why I meant
it's like the first point. Uh and
then um yeah you cannot magically like
fix that because that first point was
where the practice is. Yeah. So so so if
you go wrong there Yeah. The whole thing
is is so in a sense you have to stay
there and then go perpendicular
basically more inwards on that first
point rather than now assuming that
first point to be right and then start
building on top of it. Yeah. Yeah.
Basically you could you extend the
analogy. So, um, instead then you
realize, no, it's it's not about like
what where I'm going to walk even cuz
you cuz it's it's not like I said, you you
cuz it's it's not like I said, you you
just choose a different direction to
walk in. Um, no, that's not
it's staying in at that point where you
remain aware of your intentions. That's
the place to walk. But see that that
walking is like it's not
that's not in any of these directions.
It's perpendicular like you said. Yeah.
So
the purpose precisely like the knowledge
that you're looking for is not the type
of knowledge that's dependent on time.
That's the point. like as as would say
like uh when the monks would um when
Mara or whomever would try to tempt
them, they would say like um uh why do
you go after what what takes time when
you can go after what's presently
visible which is supposedly sensuality.
Then they twist it around and say no
actually what's presently visible is is
the dharma and sensuality is what takes
time. M so this whole principle of like
I do this practice so as to get there in
other words later in time that whole
principle is in in its nature wrong it's
wrong even if what you get to seems to
be right it's exactly what society is
yeah you work for you work for this
achievement basically uh so of course
um like enlightenment is an achievement
like it is something you have to work
for. It's not that like oh there's
nothing to attain or something but as we
said it's it's not progress north,
south, east or west. It's it's up. So
it's in a completely different direction
than everywhere else that that you go in
a completely different plane. Yeah,
that's what I was going to say even
geometrically like up wouldn't suffice.
Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. There's a sut which
talk about this space walker who wants
to find the end of the universe. But
you're not going to find the end of the
universe that way by walking. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, yeah, you could even say
it's not even like um up or down either.
It's like a fourth dimension in a sense.
You could say that. But that's uh that
that might need some qualifications, but
based on what we've said so far, that
would indeed be correct. Mhm. Um so it's
a vantage point that puts basically your
whole experience in perspective which is
perpetually available and and but the moment you
available and and but the moment you
stray from that by assuming that that
all of this is not good enough and you
should be somewhere else or it should be
different that's when you lose it. And
and that is the
the always another characteristic if
you're doing a technique, it's you're
doing it always with that implication of
like what I'm going to get from it.
always doing it with that implication of
like the emphasizing like the result
that's going to come because you don't
see like if you saw that the giving up
of craving and purification of the mind
lies right lies like in the present
uh why would you why would you do the
technique? It would make no sense. It's
like like
um if I'm already where I need to be,
why would I why would I just Yeah. up on
a car and then start driving somewhere.
Yeah. So if out of ignorance somebody
accepts a certain direction where the
method or techniques takes them and and
then based on that they become inspired
then start to practice. Now then either
most people don't have enough discipline
so they already halfway through cancers
and start doing something else. That's
what happens. But if somebody is a bit
more diligent they might stay on that
track. But even if they do then let's
say for the sake of hypothesis attain
that result that's from the beginning
they were after the only thing they
actually attain is their own ignorance
because their acceptance of that result
was fully tainted by their ignorance.
Well in other words they just keep going
around in circles. It's a it's a
actually that's a good good
um that image of this uh prohasa the one
who was running to the end of the world.
Yeah and never actually got there. No,
that's that's a good image for for
exactly what happens when like when
you're chasing this this knowledge that
comes from like later. It's always going
to you're always going to be able to get
more perceptions, more insights, more
in-depth, focus on it even more and get
even more detailed understanding of it.
And people can build a whole life around
that to the point that ironically they
sit still for 10 hours a day because
they have this attitude of wanting to
get something. So they're still running
mentally even though their whole
environment is fixed, quiet, forced
precepts, monk, sit on my cushion, they
don't understand that attitude, they
will be running. M and and it's it's
also it it does tend to to tie in with
the fact that
um yeah if you have
been unrestrained in your life
uh as people usually are then almost
anything will kind of take you in the
opposite direction. So almost anything
you do uh you just sit down and just the
fact that you're no longer engaging in
those things that you used to do that
were unh wholesome is going to make you
calmer is going to make you like feel
better whatever. Um but see if you don't
see that the principle and the reason
why it is making you feel better is
fundamentally because of the sickness
that you had or the the like you feel
better because you were you were under a
burden that you you yourself would were
creating like also mention exactly then
you you think oh it's the technique
that's helping you with this. That's now
the other thing like for most people
taking up a method or technique will be
motivated by living a very busy and busy
and somewhat chic life and just wanting
to feel a bit more calm which is
understandable. But then from the point
of view of the actual Buddhist teaching,
why did the Buddha never even teach any
meditation to lay people in the in the
way that people now conceive meditation?
Because at all really? Yeah. Or not at
all really. Yeah. Well, we could come to
that later now, but
um because suppose he would have been
teaching some method or technique with
the aim of calming people's busy lives,
then then you might say, well, that
would be compassionate. But actually,
it's not because it doesn't address the
root of the issue. Like if you keep if
if on the account of unh wholesome
actions you you keep steering up your
own mind, then you can learn a method or
technique to in the evening calm down
again. If then the next morning you keep
steering it up that doesn't go anywhere
and never address why so if somebody
then teaches a technique that doesn't
address the origin of the problem then
you would actively blind people from
seeing what now the origin of the
problem is precisely because they now
become fascinated with tech and staying
calm just giving them a painkiller so
that then don't feel the need to fix the
yeah and then then you die from a
terminal illness so it would be better
to not do that to directly diagnose the
symptoms and then say well if you want
to have always a calm mind which doesn't
need any maintenance on your
part don't act in such a way that keeps
steering up your own mind because you
just shoot your own food that's the
reason why there's always this emphasis
on virtue and on sense restraint and
seclusion that is not because the Buddha
hadn't yet discovered some sort of
meditation method and technique because
if you emphasize that side or even if
you say anything along those lines
without actually um revealing the origin
of the problem, then you would be
leading people astray. And that is
ironically what I think we see basically
everywhere these days. Yeah. Yeah. It's
it's more entertaining for sure. It's
more entertaining to just dance around
the problem in infinite array of ways
than to actually look at it in the face
and see, oh, this is this is what it is.
And um and I mean factually in the same
way that yes it could could calm you
down uh depending on the technique I guess
uh depending on the technique I guess
but it could show you some like you
could circumstantially have
um due to no longer being as distracted
by you know worldly things and and
breaking precepts and stuff. It may give
you a better a closer recognition of
let's say your
intentions for a bit but because you
emphasize the technique
part you don't stay on that point where
you could have like actually developed
that awareness of the stuff that matters
you think it's the technique then you
you again like I said before you keep
the emphasis in the wrong place so so it
actually takes you now away from from
that middle ground where you could have
like just p pulled back from the engagement
just p pulled back from the engagement
with the world but without then falling
into another internal kind of activity
that Yeah. that you need to keep going.
Exactly. Yeah. So, so yeah like pulling
back from stuff. So in in in that sense
it wouldn't even be the technique
itself. It just it would just be the
fact that it would force you to kind of
like withdraw to to stop engaging with
things in the world and that in itself
could be the basis for the right
practice but you need to keep it there
and not then run in start running in a
different direction. Yeah.